{
  "reference_number": "10957",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "2050 is a somewhat arbitrary date and it may be too late to avoid catastrophic effects. I hope we proceed with maximum urgency and\n\n get to our targets earlier."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The balancing of NO2, CO2 and CH4 is a complex economic and mathematical problem. There are not many chances to get this right.\n Listen to the best economists you can find on this problem. This seems like an obvious thing to say but I've seen the best minds\n\n sidelined many times before."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Imagine those creative solutions will come from everywhere and find ways to make space for them. There need to be many, many\n solutions to this - some will seem counter-intuitive and some will defy accepted wisdom. Inform the people as best you can and trust\n\n them to find solutions with you."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - but only to a sooner date. We already know the current situation is perilous."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I would add that the reason things are so bad now is that people simply failed to understand the problem for the last 30 years.\n\nUnderstanding that misunderstanding is a field of its own and is perhaps the most important. People's understanding of the current\nproblem is still terribly vague. Communicating this problem is leading people to an entirely new understanding of 'world'. The term 'Act\n\nof God' - which was framed in law - has now lost its purchase. So much participation is required and how can that be achieved without\ndisrupting some of our most enduring reflections. Its like removing dairy ingredients from the Edmonds cookbook. Imagine a world\n\nwhere climate change was as tangible as the presence of war. The stories we share from those times would inform us now. We would\n(collectively) be doing more. Surely."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "People can't participate usefully in a problem they can't understand. And people don't understand this problem. I've talked to many\n\neducated left leaning environmentalists and rarely found any that understand why and how dairy affects global warming. We should\nhave been teaching this in schools for the last thirty years. Imagine a future where people are incented to understand the problem for\n\ntwo reasons. Firstly, they keep hearing stories and seeing footage of sandy beaches, green pastures, extraordinary kinds of fruit and\nanimals they can't possibly imagine. And they need to know what happened to all of that. Secondly because they live within systems\n\nthat prevent them from using fuels or creating food the way we do now. And they are too hot, or too cold or too hungry. In that future\npeople will understand about CO2 and methane. The atmospheric budget will stand over them and the story of global warming will be\ndeeply entrenched creation mythology. And they will wonder at us and our ignorance. The haze we've allowed ourselves to live in.\n\nThe time we wasted. The Zero Carbon Bill says nothing about finding ways to tell the story now - about taking some of the insights\nwe know will exist in the minds of our descendents and placing them here in our time. We try not to use alarmist talk - but we can't do\n\nthat by not sounding the alarm. I am relieved beyond measure to see this consultation paper and I am grateful to the thousands to\nsacrificed to make it real. I feel confident in the purpose and direction of the interim commission and the climate change ministry. I\n\nwould just add, again, that if we can make the story of carbon and our debt to energy the first thing we tell our children now, their\nchildren will be better off. We know they will look back at us in horror because we know they will live in a world where doing what we\ndo is a crime against humanity. I want them to see that, finally, at some point, we got it and we came together and we tried. Finally, I\n\nfear that we may be kidding ourselves with dairy. Its almost an act of treason to say this in NZ but perhaps food from livestock ought\nto go the way torque from livestock did at the start of the industrial revolution. Since Shane Ardern's tractor climbed the steps of\n\nparliament we have been trying to reverse engineer the cow. While millenia of evolutionary source code is deleted around us we\npersist with the notion that one single process - enteric fermentation, can be fundamentally altered with a pill. That sounds like an\n\nalchemist's quest, not a scientist's. If this is a mistake then the market will make the alterations for us. And we will regret some great\nlosses."
    }
  ]
}
